Kirsten Gotting

k.gotting@gmail.com http://kirstengotting.com

I am a Bioinformaticist in the lab of Dr. Alejandro Sánchez Alvarado. I have worked on various projects for the lab, including RNA-seq analysis on various organisms, proteomics analysis and genome annotation.

Genomes ability to be plastic in the face of evolutionary pressure, with the circumstances and conditions determining why certain genes are maintained, duplicated, or removed drives me to continue researching and learning in the field of Biology.

SKILLS

Unix • Bioconductor • MAKER Tuxedo Suite • Trinity Parallel Computing • tidyverse BUSCO • Rmarkdown/knitr Data Visualization • Git.

Programming

R • Python • Bash • MySQL https://github.com/kirstengott

Analysis

- RNA-sea
- Genome Annotation
- Isoform
- Gene Ontology
- Motif
- MudPIT Proteomics

EDUCATION

MS in Biology 2014

Emphasis: Bioinformatics/Genomics University of Oregon, Eugene, OR

BA in Biology 2013

Minors: Chemistry, Spanish University of Oregon, Eugene, OR

PUBLICATIONS

Davies, Erin L., Kai Lei, Christopher W. Seidel, Amanda E. Kroesen, Sean A. McKinney, Longhua Guo, Sofia MC Robb, Eric J. Ross, Kirsten Gotting, and Aleiandro Sánchez Alvarado. "Embryonic origin of adult stem cells required for tissue homeostasis and regeneration." eLife 6 (2017): e21052.

Luttrell, Shawn M., Kirsten Gotting, Eric Ross, Alejandro Sánchez Alvarado, and Billie J. Swalla. "Head Regeneration in Hemichordates Is Not a Strict Recapitulation of Development." Developmental Dynamics (2016).

Lei, Kai, Hanh Thi-Kim Vu, Ryan D. Mohan, Sean A. McKinney, Chris W. Seidel, Richard Alexander, Kirsten Gotting, Jerry L. Workman, and Alejandro Sánchez Alvarado. "Egf Signaling Directs Neoblast Repopulation by Regulating Asymmetric Cell Division in Planarians." Developmental Cell 38, no. 4 (2016): 413-429.

Robb, Sofia, Kirsten Gotting, Eric Ross, and Alejandro Sánchez Alvarado. "SmedGD 2.0: The Schmidtea mediterranea genome database." genesis 53, no. 8 (2015): 535-546.

EXPERIENCE

Bioinformaticist

October 2014 - Current

Stowers Institute for Medical Research - Kansas City, MO Sánchez Lab - HHMI

- -Set up and maintained a genome browser, and created pipelines for gene annotation and RNA-seq data analysis for Nothobranchius furzeri.
- -Contributed to creation of SmedGD 2.0, a genome database for Schmidtea mediterranea.

Bioinformatics Intern January 2014 - September 2014

Stowers Institute for Medical Research - Kansas City, MO Sánchez Lab - HHMI

-Developed a self-documenting RNA-seq analysis pipeline for analysis of data from non-model organisms, compatible with parallel computing environments. Created interactive web apps for accessible data viewing.

Graduate Teaching Fellow September 2013 – December 2013

University of Oregon - Eugene, OR

-Instructed students in initial course of first year introductory biology course.

Line/Lab Assitant

October 2010 - June 2013

Zebrafish International Resource Center - Eugene, OR

-Worked to maintain and propagate zebrafish lines for shipping to domestic and international research labs.

Undergraduate Research Assistant April 2012 - September 2012

University of Oregon - Eugene, OR

Selker Lab

-Creation and characterization of mutant strains of Neurospora crassa defective in methylation capabilities. Knowledge of UV mutagenesis, selective mutant screens, DNA isolation, southern blots.